{"test_questions": [[{"question": "In a four stage compressor, if the pressure at the first and third stage are 1 bar and 16 bar, then the delivery pressure at the fourth stage will be", "opta": "1 bar", "optb": "16 bar", "optc": "64 bar", "optd": "256 bar", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The compressed air may be used", "opta": "in gas turbine plants", "optb": "for operating pneumatic drills", "optc": "in starting and supercharging of I.C. engines", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rocket works with maximum overall efficiency when air-craft velocity is __________ the jet velocity.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "one-half", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The volumetric efficiency for reciprocating air compressors is about", "opta": "10 to 40%", "optb": "40 to 60%", "optc": "60 to 70%", "optd": "70 to 90%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum temperature in a gas turbine is", "opta": "200\u00b0C", "optb": "500\u00b0C", "optc": "700\u00b0C", "optd": "1000\u00b0C", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rotary compressors are suitable for large discharge of air at low pressure.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stagnation pressure rise in a centrifugal compressor takes place", "opta": "in the diffuser only", "optb": "in the impeller only", "optc": "in the diffuser and impeller", "optd": "in the inlet guide vanes only", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total heat rejected in a reciprocating air compressor is equal to the sum of the heat rejected during polytropic compression per kg of air and heat rejected in the intercooler per kg of air.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a jet propulsion", "opta": "the propulsive matter is ejected from within the propelled body", "optb": "the propulsive matter is caused to flow around the propelled body", "optc": "its functioning does not depend upon presence of air", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An open cycle gas turbine works on the same cycle as that of a closed cycle gas turbine.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?", "opta": "In a two stage reciprocating air compressor with complete intercooling, maximum work is saved.", "optb": "The minimum work required for a two stage reciprocating air compressor is double the work required for each stage.", "optc": "The ratio of the volume of free air delivery per stroke to the swept volume of the piston is called volumetric efficiency.", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a single acting reciprocating compressor, the suction, compression and delivery of air takes place in __________ of the piston.", "opta": "one stroke", "optb": "two strokes", "optc": "three strokes", "optd": "four strokes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The increase in pressure in a vane blower takes place first due to compression and then due to back flow of air.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum delivery pressure in a rotary air compressor is", "opta": "10 bar", "optb": "20 bar", "optc": "30 bar", "optd": "50 bar", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a compressor is expressed in", "opta": "kg/m2", "optb": "kg/m3", "optc": "m3/min", "optd": "m3/kg", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Intercooling in multi-stage compressors is done", "opta": "to cool the air during compression", "optb": "to cool the air at delivery", "optc": "to enable compression in two stages", "optd": "to minimise the work of compression", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a two stage reciprocating compressor, compression from p1 to p3 is with perfect intercooling and no pressure losses. If compression in both the cylinders follows the same polytropic process and the atmospheric pressure is pa, then the intermediate pressure p2 is given by", "opta": "p2 = (p1 + p3)/2", "optb": "p2 = p1.p3", "optc": "P2 = Pa x p3/p1", "optd": "p2 = pa p3/p1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of workdone per cycle to the stroke volume of the compressor is known as", "opta": "compressor capacity", "optb": "compression ratio", "optc": "compressor efficiency", "optd": "mean effective pressure", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The clearance volume in the compressor is kept minimum because it effects on volumetric efficiency.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The inlet pressure is always __________ the discharge pressure.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "The ratio of the discharge pressure to the inlet pressure of air is called compressor efficiency.", "optb": "The compression ratio for the compressor is always greater than unity.", "optc": "The compressor capacity is the ratio of workdone per cycle to the stroke volume.", "optd": "During isothermal compression of air, the workdone in a compressor is maximum.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the aircraft propellers", "opta": "the propulsive matter is ejected from within the propelled body", "optb": "the propulsive matter is caused to flow around the propelled body", "optc": "its functioning does not depend upon the presence of air", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of rotary compressor used in gas turbines, is of", "opta": "centrifugal type", "optb": "axial flow type", "optc": "radial flow type", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The volume of air delivered by the compressor is called", "opta": "free air delivery", "optb": "compressor capacity", "optc": "swept volume", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a jet engine is higher at", "opta": "low speeds", "optb": "high speeds", "optc": "low altitudes", "optd": "high altitudes", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In axial flow compressor, exit flow angle deviation from the blade angle is a function of", "opta": "blade camber", "optb": "blade camber and incidence angle", "optc": "space-chord ratio", "optd": "blade camber and space-chord ratio", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rotary compressors are used for delivering", "opta": "small quantities of air at high pressures", "optb": "large quantities of air at high pressures", "optc": "small quantities of air at low pressures", "optd": "large quantities of air at low pressures", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Workdone by a two-stage reciprocating air compressor per cycle is equal to the workdone in LP. cylinder and H.P. cylinder.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rotary compressor is driven by an", "opta": "electric motor", "optb": "engine", "optc": "either (a) or (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a centrifugal compressor, an increase in speed at a given pressure ratio causes", "opta": "increase in flow", "optb": "decrease in flow", "optc": "increase in efficiency", "optd": "increase in flow and decrease in efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A large clearance Volume in a reciprocating compressor results in", "opta": "reduced volume flow rate", "optb": "increased volume flow rate", "optc": "lower suction pressure", "optd": "lower delivery pressure", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A closed cycle gas turbine gives __________ efficiency as compared to an open cycle gas turbine.", "opta": "same", "optb": "lower", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gas turbine as compared to steam turbine", "opta": "requires less space for installation", "optb": "has compressor and combustion chamber", "optc": "has less efficiency", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Intercooling in gas turbines", "opta": "decreases net output but increases thermal efficiency", "optb": "increases net output but decreases thermal efficiency", "optc": "decreases net output and thermal efficiency both", "optd": "increases net output and thermal efficiency both", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the temperature of air leaving the intercooler, in a two stage compression with intercooler, is __________ the original atmospheric air temperature, then the intercooling is known as perfect or complete intercooling.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The actual volume of air delivered by a compressor, When reduced to the normal temperature and pressure conditions is called compressor capacity.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The compression ratio in a gas turbine is", "opta": "4", "optb": "1", "optc": "9", "optd": "12", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Intercooling in compressors results in saving of power in compressing given volume of air to a given pressure.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Only rocket engines can be propelled to space because", "opta": "they can generate very high thrust", "optb": "they have high propulsion efficiency", "optc": "these engines can work on several fuels", "optd": "they are not air-breathing engines", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum combustion pressure in gas turbine is __________ as compared to I.C. engine.", "opta": "more", "optb": "less", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An aftercooler is used to", "opta": "remove impurities from air", "optb": "reduce volume of air", "optc": "cause moisture and oil vapour to drop out", "optd": "cool the air", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High air-fuel ratio in gas turbines", "opta": "increases power output", "optb": "improves thermal efficiency", "optc": "reduces exhaust temperature", "optd": "do not damage turbine blades", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the volume of free air delivery per stroke to the swept volume of the piston, is known as", "opta": "compressor efficiency", "optb": "volumetric efficiency", "optc": "isothermal efficiency", "optd": "mechanical efficiency", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If p1, is the pressure of air entering the L.P. cylinder and p2 is the pressure of air leaving the L.P. cylinder (or intercooler pressure), then the ratio of cylinder diameters for a single acting, two stage reciprocating air compressor with complete intercooling is given by (where D1 = Dia. of L.P. cylinder, and D2 = Dia. of H.P. cylinder)", "opta": "D1/D2 = p1p2", "optb": "D1/D2 = p1/p2", "optc": "D1/D2 = p2/p1", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the indicated power to the shaft power or brake power of the motor or engine required to drive the compressor, is called", "opta": "compressor efficiency", "optb": "volumetric efficiency", "optc": "isothermal efficiency", "optd": "mechanical efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The increase in pressure in a roots blower is entirely due to back flow of air.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of rotary compressor used in aeroplanes, is of", "opta": "centrifugal type", "optb": "axial flow type", "optc": "radial flow type", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An axial compressor gives optimum performance at high speeds and large volume flows.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reciprocating air compressor, the compression work per kg of air", "opta": "increases as clearance volume increases", "optb": "decreases as clearance volume increases", "optc": "is independent of clearance volume", "optd": "increases as clearance volume decreases", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The degree of reaction in an axial flow compressor is defined as the ratio of static enthalpy rise in the", "opta": "rotor to static enthalpy rise in the stator", "optb": "stator to static enthalpy rise in the rotor", "optc": "rotor to static enthalpy rise in the stage", "optd": "stator to static enthalpy rise in the stage", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}